<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Christopher J. Friedline, Ph.D. - Blog</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chris.friedline.net/</id><updated>2018-03-23T10:38:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>So, yeah…</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2018/Mar/23/so-yeah/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-23T10:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-23T10:38:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2018-03-23:/posts/2018/Mar/23/so-yeah/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I know this is out of date, but hopefully more content soon on new pubs and
other exciting developments and&amp;nbsp;musings.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I know this is out of date, but hopefully more content soon on new pubs and
other exciting developments and&amp;nbsp;musings.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Winter school in Weggis</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2015/Mar/25/winter-school-in-weggis/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-25T15:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-25T15:13:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2015-03-25:/posts/2015/Mar/25/winter-school-in-weggis/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is just a place-holder for now, largely to get myself moving on writing all of this up. Until then, here are some of the&amp;nbsp;basics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was one of five instructors for the &lt;a href="http://www.adaptation.ethz.ch/education/winter-school-2015.html"&gt;Bioinformatics for Adaptation Genomics&lt;/a&gt;: Adaptation genomics in the realm of Next-Generation Sequencing data analysis course, held …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is just a place-holder for now, largely to get myself moving on writing all of this up. Until then, here are some of the&amp;nbsp;basics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was one of five instructors for the &lt;a href="http://www.adaptation.ethz.ch/education/winter-school-2015.html"&gt;Bioinformatics for Adaptation Genomics&lt;/a&gt;: Adaptation genomics in the realm of Next-Generation Sequencing data analysis course, held in Weggis, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CH&lt;/span&gt; from March 1 to March 7,&amp;nbsp;2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My day-long &lt;a href="https://github.com/cfriedline/congen2015"&gt;lecture and exercises&lt;/a&gt; focused on evolutionary genetics (genomics) and methods for detecting assocations, among genotypes, traits, and&amp;nbsp;evironments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My wife went,&amp;nbsp;too!  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The trip was wholly&amp;nbsp;awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More later, I&amp;nbsp;promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="teaching"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="ipython"></category></entry><entry><title>On preprints, war, and the end of the world</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Dec/10/on-preprints-war-and-the-end-of-the-world/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-10T10:31:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-12-10T10:31:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-12-10:/posts/2014/Dec/10/on-preprints-war-and-the-end-of-the-world/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, so this post is mostly about preprints.&amp;nbsp;Onward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some&amp;nbsp;background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask a high-energy physicist (does anyone really &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; one?) about using a
preprint server and chances are that not only have they deposited papers at one
(like &lt;a href="http://www.arxiv.org"&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;), chances are the discussion of whether or
not to do so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, so this post is mostly about preprints.&amp;nbsp;Onward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some&amp;nbsp;background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask a high-energy physicist (does anyone really &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; one?) about using a
preprint server and chances are that not only have they deposited papers at one
(like &lt;a href="http://www.arxiv.org"&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;), chances are the discussion of whether or
not to do so either doesn&amp;#8217;t make any sense (because&amp;#8230;physicist) or is silly
(because&amp;#8230;physicist). Jokes about our mathy colleagues aside, the practice of
posting research to their larger scientific community before or during the peer
review process, which in their case can sometimes take an inordinately long
time, become part of their culture over two decades&amp;nbsp;ago. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started in the early 90&amp;#8217;s, arXiv is currently housed at
&lt;a href="http://www.cornell.edu"&gt;Cornell University&lt;/a&gt; and currently serves the fields of
Physics, Mathematics, Computer Science, Quantitative Biology, Quantitative
Finance, and Statistics.  As of today, it provides open access to 995,193
e-prints, not shabby at all considering that only 306 papers were submitted in
1991, the first year. Though there are other minor players in the game, the main
additional preprint servers are: &lt;a href="http://www.biorxiv.org"&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://precedings.nature.com"&gt;Nature Precedings&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="http://www.peerj.com"&gt;PeerJ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you&amp;#8217;re looking for a thorough review of preprint culture in biology,
this post will not be the place. There have been others who invested the time
and energy to do that, and if you&amp;#8217;re interested in what others have to say (and
you should be), There are links at the &lt;a href="#links"&gt;bottom of this post&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;what this post will be about&lt;/strong&gt; is a recent preprint experience I had at
&lt;a href="http://evolfri.blogspot.com"&gt;EvolFri&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why all this talk of preprints, Chris? Glad you asked. At a recent
installment of EvolFri, we read a paper that, though now published in a
highly-read, though perhaps not the most technical, journal, started out as a
preprint.  Not only did it start out as a preprint, we even knew about it as
soon as it came out (i.e., social media) there. Awesome, I thought: a preprint
relevant to the work we do in our lab, one we can potentially read at our
weekly &amp;#8220;meeting,&amp;#8221; and written by scientists we respect.  Which brings me to
&lt;strong&gt;Preprint Benefit #1&lt;/strong&gt;: we got access to the work before it went through
the formal processes of editorial consent and peer&amp;nbsp;review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first read through it, as with most papers I read for the first time, caused
no great distress. I made note of some sections and sentences to come back to
later, which of course I didn&amp;#8217;t (something about a road, paving, and best
intentions?). The version that we actually read for EvolFri, however, was
different enough, post-publication, that the group (myself included) had some
not insignificant concerns. On the surface, the points made in the paper were
harmless enough in most cases, but given the high-degree of readership of the
eventual journal and who in the community was likely to read the article (e.g.,
outside grant reviewers), alarm bells started to go off. This leads right into
&lt;strong&gt;Preprint Benefit #2&lt;/strong&gt;: the ability for the scientific community to interact
with the paper. This interaction, I imagine can come in many forms: 1) Emailing
the authors with comments, 2) Posting comments directly to the paper (or an
aggregator site, like &lt;a href="http://www.haldanessieve.org"&gt;Haldane&amp;#8217;s Sieve&lt;/a&gt;), or using
the special powers of social media to comment to the world (+dog). In fact, in
this case, comments were indeed solicited by the authors when the preprint was&amp;nbsp;advertised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we agreed with the majority of the points made in the paper, the concerns
we had after it was all over were, in our (now red-cheeked) opinions, worthy of
larger scientific discussion/criticism. If only we had a forum in which to
address these issues before they were formally published. If&amp;nbsp;only&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s talk about &lt;strong&gt;Preprint Problem #1&lt;/strong&gt;: there&amp;#8217;s no incentive to participate
other than to publish. Open science is awesome, a great idea, supported by large
numbers of scientists in our field and others, and can only do great things,
right? &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, that&amp;#8217;s well-established. Unfortunately, the current climates of
Biology and Biomedicine do: little, if anything, to reward the publishing of
preprint articles; little, if anything, to reward having your preprint article
cited, and nothing at all to reward participating in the process of preprint
review. &lt;strong&gt;Why in the name of Darwin&lt;/strong&gt; would any scientist in their right mind,
who is already committed to 50% research, 50% teaching, 50% service, and 50%
outreach (yes, I can add), devote any time to providing comments to preprints?
That lots of scientists are &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/12N0mPN"&gt;not in their right mind&lt;/a&gt; in
the first place, notwithstanding, they don&amp;#8217;t.  They simply don&amp;#8217;t, and won&amp;#8217;t
until something changes with the current state of Big Business Academia, where
pressures to train, publish, teach, and serve compete with turning the wheels
of the &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1ByOjEF"&gt;overhead machine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 1: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sKFRSL4wpcY&amp;amp;spfreload=10"&gt;fix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did click the fix link?  No, well,
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JjLmY0SxoWM"&gt;then there is no pleasing you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joking aside, the only way this system is going to change, I think, is
for a few brave souls to stand up and fight the &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221;.  I&amp;#8217;m talking about
picketing, walk-outs, and rioting, if you have to.  Hell, take a
student or two hostage (not your own, though, they have work to do). Even,
now bare with me, lecturing without PowerPoint can&amp;#8217;t be off the&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all of that seems too tame, I understand. Maybe instead of those options, we
can all just come together at meetings, or over the social internet media site
thingies, and decide this is something that we want to do (or not) and move
forward. Lobby with colleagues in your department. Meet with your colleagues in
Physics. Come together as a community and make those above us, at least in
title, understand why this part of your 50% service is valuable and&amp;nbsp;rewardable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprint repositories can help, too&lt;/strong&gt;. In addition to the lobbying, blogging,
and publishing that they already do, providing a way to validate and query
contributions of outside reviewers/commentors would be a great first step, so
when Dr. Friedline says he reviewed 365 pre-prints last year, his boss can
easily validate&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="links"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://news.sciencemag.org/biology/2014/11/biorxiv-1-year-promising-start"&gt;BioRxiv at 1 year: A promising start&lt;/a&gt;
   (Kaiser, Science Insider,&amp;nbsp;2014)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.plosbiology.org/article/info:doi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pbio.1001563#s4"&gt;The Case for Open Preprints in Biology&lt;/a&gt; (Desjardins-Proulx, et al. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLOS&lt;/span&gt; Biology,&amp;nbsp;2013)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/preprints-come-to-life-1.14140"&gt;Preprints come to live&lt;/a&gt; (Callaway, Nature News,&amp;nbsp;2013)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amapress.gen.cam.ac.uk/?p=1316"&gt;Why I support BioRxiv and the emerging culture of preprint servers&lt;/a&gt; (Martinez-Arias, Cambridge, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;,&amp;nbsp;2013)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="papers"></category><category term="openscience"></category></entry><entry><title>New microsatellite paper out!</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Dec/08/new-microsatellite-paper-out/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-08T22:51:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-12-08T22:51:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-12-08:/posts/2014/Dec/08/new-microsatellite-paper-out/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m late in putting this up, too, but a big thanks to Serena and Clint for
the opportunity to be a part of their work in this cool&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12686-014-0380-8"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Caplinsetal2014_PrimerNote.png", width=500&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m late in putting this up, too, but a big thanks to Serena and Clint for
the opportunity to be a part of their work in this cool&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12686-014-0380-8"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Caplinsetal2014_PrimerNote.png", width=500&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="paper"></category></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry certified!</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Dec/08/software-carpentry-certified/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-08T22:37:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-12-08T22:37:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-12-08:/posts/2014/Dec/08/software-carpentry-certified/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a little late in getting up here, achievment having
been unlocked last May, but better late than&amp;nbsp;never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m very proud to be part of this
&lt;a href="http://www.software-carpentry.ort"&gt;organization&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to
teaching more workshops in&amp;nbsp;2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/swc_cert.png", width="500px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a little late in getting up here, achievment having
been unlocked last May, but better late than&amp;nbsp;never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m very proud to be part of this
&lt;a href="http://www.software-carpentry.ort"&gt;organization&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to
teaching more workshops in&amp;nbsp;2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/swc_cert.png", width="500px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="swcarpentry"></category><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>How we should (and should not) collaborate</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Oct/14/how-we-should-and-should-not-collaborate/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-14T14:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-14T14:20:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-10-14:/posts/2014/Oct/14/how-we-should-and-should-not-collaborate/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who know me (all 10 of you), you are well aware of
where I stand on open science and, more recently, on
reproducibility. For everyone else, I believe strongly in open
science, open writing, open collaboration, accountability, and
documentation. I have nothing to hide when it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who know me (all 10 of you), you are well aware of
where I stand on open science and, more recently, on
reproducibility. For everyone else, I believe strongly in open
science, open writing, open collaboration, accountability, and
documentation. I have nothing to hide when it comes to how I do
science, and I expect the same from my collaborators. With regard to
reproducibility, I promise to make every effort to write methods with
enough detail that will enable you, albeit with some skill required,
to reproduce my results. I will not, most likely, provide anyone with
fully turn-key solutions (e.g, &lt;a href="http://www.docker.com"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt;). I don&amp;#8217;t believe that&amp;#8217;s my job as
a scientist, and until someone convinces me otherwise, that&amp;#8217;s where I
stand.  All that being said, &lt;strong&gt;I welcome collaboration, and would love
to work with you&lt;/strong&gt;. Yes, even you. And&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent collaboration of mine has reminded me how much there is for
some of us to learn when it comes to working in, for lack of a better
term, an open science framework. First thing&amp;#8217;s first: I don&amp;#8217;t expect
anyone to become a LaTeX expert overnight or understand how to cherry
pick changes across git branches, but here is a list of a few things
that I would prefer not to (read: likely won&amp;#8217;t)&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Microsoft&amp;nbsp;Word&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email infinite copies of documents&amp;nbsp;around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a sharing solution (e.g, Google Drive, Dropbox) to you,
only to turn around and then email you&amp;nbsp;documents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage in endless email threads about changes to documents, tables,
figures,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these, here&amp;#8217;s my preferred working environment and how it
might benefit us to be the most productive when working on a paper&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use&amp;nbsp;LaTeX:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on and on, but my main reasons for writing this way&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citation management (BibTeX, AucTex, RefTeX,&amp;nbsp;etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plain-text documents lend themselves to version&amp;nbsp;control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version control provides a natural way to collaborate (i.e., via
&lt;a href="http://www.github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s available everywhere, even on the web via
       &lt;a href="http://www.authorea.com"&gt;Authorea&lt;/a&gt;,
       &lt;a href="http://www.writelatex.com"&gt;WriteLaTeX&lt;/a&gt;,
       &lt;a href="http://www.sharelatex.com"&gt;ShareLaTeX&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It makes journal submission much&amp;nbsp;easier!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use&amp;nbsp;git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are many ways to version control, but this is what I
prefer. It makes working collaboratively possible while keeping
changes safe and contributions accounted-for. It&amp;#8217;s also what we teach
at &lt;a href="http://www.software-carpentry.com"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; so what
kind of instructor would I be if I didn&amp;#8217;t use it? It also gets us away
from the (just plain) nasty paradigm of emailing documents around like
&lt;code&gt;results_1_cf_1_2_modified_cf2_modified_5.csv&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use email for its&amp;nbsp;purpose&amp;#8230;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To tell me what I a good job I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To set up a time so we can have a conference call to tell me what a
   good job I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To allow me a place to tell you what a good job you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get the&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use collaboration tools for&amp;nbsp;collaboration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could mean many things to many people.  To me, it means something like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we have documents on Google Drive and you want to chat about it or make changes,
do those things using the tools in Google Drive. This way, we can keep track of
work and requests for work without going completely&amp;nbsp;nuts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to make a significant change to a document we&amp;#8217;re writing together on
Github, submit an issue or pull request for the same reasons as&amp;nbsp;above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please don&amp;#8217;t make me log into the same Google Drive that I&amp;#8217;ve
shared to you, click the same &lt;code&gt;Download&lt;/code&gt; button you could click,
download the files to my computer, and then email them to&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;For Pete&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;sake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please, please, please, take the time to consider what I&amp;#8217;m saying and
how you&amp;#8217;re currently doing things. Might there be some upfront,
getting-used-to-it-ivness? Sure.  I promise, though, it will be worth
it. We have so much technology to help us be the most productive
scientists we can be, and from my own experiences, we are all much
happier when things go smoothly and don&amp;#8217;t have to spend time on
thoughts like &amp;#8220;in what folder did I put that most recent version of
that&amp;nbsp;file.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concludes rant&amp;nbsp;#546.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="collaborate"></category><category term="git"></category><category term="latex"></category><category term="openscience"></category></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry at Penn Redux</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Sep/30/software-carpentry-at-penn-redux/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-30T22:02:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-09-30T22:02:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-09-30:/posts/2014/Sep/30/software-carpentry-at-penn-redux/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro and shell (day&amp;nbsp;1)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has been a long time coming, since
&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/rdavidmurray"&gt;R. David Murray&lt;/a&gt; and I taught
the &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/2014-08-21-upenn"&gt;bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; on
8/21-22/2014. Sadly, I&amp;#8217;ve been struggling with wrangling my own data,
collaborators, going to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt;, planning sampling trips, helping to train
the new undergrads in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro and shell (day&amp;nbsp;1)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has been a long time coming, since
&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/rdavidmurray"&gt;R. David Murray&lt;/a&gt; and I taught
the &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/2014-08-21-upenn"&gt;bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; on
8/21-22/2014. Sadly, I&amp;#8217;ve been struggling with wrangling my own data,
collaborators, going to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt;, planning sampling trips, helping to train
the new undergrads in the lab, and about 1000 other things since
then. Luckily, no one reads my&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The planning for this bootcamp came together very quickly, and I think
all parties can agree that some things could have been tightened up a
little bit. With that said, I think it went off really well. It was an
amazing experience both as a scientist to be immersed in that
stimulating of an environment and as an instructor having the good
fortune of a body of students so excited and (dare I say) hungry for
the material. I was extremely proud to be representing Software
Carpentry, and I hope we did the name justice when all was said and&amp;nbsp;done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve ready my &lt;a href="/pages/about.html"&gt;bio&lt;/a&gt;, you already know that I lived
around the Philadelphia area for several years before moving to
Richmond, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt;. It was great to be back in the city and having dinner at
old (&lt;a href="http://www.monkscafe.com"&gt;Monk&amp;#8217;s Cafe&lt;/a&gt;) and new
(&lt;a href="http://crowandthepitcher.com"&gt;Crow and the Pitcher&lt;/a&gt;) places. The
folks at Penn were able to secure us great rooms at
&lt;a href="http://clubquarters.com/philadelphia"&gt;Club Quarters&lt;/a&gt;, too, providing a
great walk over to campus to begin and end the&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David and I arrived early on the first day in case anyone had issues
with getting the required software up and going before we got
started. No one really needed our help for this part, so we spent the
time getting our laptops connected to the projector, finding the chalk
(I love chalk!) for the boards, and planning the day. We settled on
each teaching for 1/2 of each day with David handling Bash and Python
and me up for git and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;. I sent out a few tweets about this, but I
feel like we (myself included) were all quite fortunate to have a core
CPython maintainer going over shell and Python lessons. Having not
taught a huge amount (by his own admission), I thought David delivered
all of his lessons with an expected level of mastery. That afternoon,
I taught the git material, but perhaps in a different way than&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cleaning example&amp;nbsp;files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We needed to distribute the examples to the
course participants, but when I went out to the bootcamp site, they
already had the examples worked through in the lesson notebooks. As a
quick hack, I set these up cleaned versions using another
&lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/2014-08-21-upenn/blob/gh-pages/create_clean_dist_files.ipynb"&gt;IPython notebook&lt;/a&gt;
to run through the examples in the bootcamp course material and strip
out the output cells and zip it all up nice and pretty-like. Seemed to
work pretty well, so if anyone wants it, please feel free to use
it. Moving forward, it would be nice if we had clean versions
committed to the repos from the start, I&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching&amp;nbsp;git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the instructor training (did I mention this was my first
time teaching a bootcamp?) and after, it was never clear to me the
direction with which the lessons were to be delivered. It seemed to
be entirely up to the particular instructor, a situation in which I&amp;#8217;m
very comfortable, but I didn&amp;#8217;t want to step on any toes. Reading
through the git material, I thought it would make much more sense to,
sort-of, pseudo-flip, the lesson material. In this way, I could
introduce some of the material (say 15 minutes a time) and then set
the bootcamp attendees off and running with the lessons as lined out
in the course material. I also paired them up to work on a
collaborative scenario in which the work done in previous lessons was
shared via pull requests to their partner&amp;#8217;s repository on github
(which also got them all github&amp;nbsp;accounts!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of my own delivery, I did something perhaps unorthodox. &lt;strong&gt;I
taught git without a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; and without dropping to the shell&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead,
I used an &lt;a href="http://www.ipython.org"&gt;IPython notebook&lt;/a&gt;. Well, not just a
plain notebook, but one with
&lt;a href="https://github.com/damianavila/live_reveal"&gt;Damian Avila&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s live
reveal slideshow extension and the &lt;code&gt;%rehashx&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;%automagic on&lt;/code&gt;
magics. I did this for a couple of reasons: 1) to introduce the
students to the IPython notebook which they would be seeing when David
taught Python and 2) to have a continuity in my lessons without having
to have presentation slides dropping out to a shell and back again. I
was very pleased with out it all went down on this front - there were
some minor glitches related to the projector and getting confused with
too many Google Chrome windows, but that was all quite
self-inflicted. Having a ready shell integrated with presentation
slides was, from my point of view, a pretty effective way to deliver
the material. I would welcome feed back here, especially from the
bootcamp participants on how it actually went over. The notebook
containing the slides can be downloaded
&lt;a href="https://github.com/cfriedline/swc-slides/blob/master/2014-08-21-upenn/git.ipynb"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with that out of the way, the git lessons in the course material
were already quite solid, so I didn&amp;#8217;t really add anything there except
to pair the students up for pushing and pulling in two common
collaborative models: 1) granting access to collaborators to your own
repository and 2) forking a repository and submitting pull
requests. We discussed the safety and pain of both approaches and from
the comments and questions, it was pretty clear to me that we
accomplished several&amp;nbsp;things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That git (or version control, in general) is&amp;nbsp;important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That using git isn&amp;#8217;t too&amp;nbsp;hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That collaborating using version control is entirely within&amp;nbsp;reach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to hear the immediate feed back from both PIs and their
students that the skills we were presenting to them were going to be
put into practice immediately, a fact that&amp;#8217;s both stimulating as an
instructor and satisfying as an advocate for best practices in the
real&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The room and the&amp;nbsp;Etherpad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most Software Carpentry bootcamps, we set up and monitored
an &lt;a href="https://swcarpentry.etherpad.mozilla.org/2014-08-21-upenn?"&gt;Etherpad&lt;/a&gt;. I thought
this was particularly effective, especially given the room&amp;nbsp;setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/swc_upenn.png" width="500px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what I alluded to earlier about some of things not
coming together as they normally would have given more time, is that
we were allocated an auditorium setting in which to run the
bootcamp. This meant that it would be difficult for us to get to
students in the middle of the rows to help them, and also that the
highly effective &amp;#8220;Post-it barometer system of understanding&amp;#8221; could not
be used because we couldn&amp;#8217;t see people&amp;#8217;s laptops to which the notes
would be stuck. This is where the Etherpad came in, much more so on
day one than day two (not sure why). I was able to answer many
questions on it while David was teaching. David was able to monitor it
while I was teaching as well. I&amp;#8217;ve heard reports that instructors
often keep their own copy open while they&amp;#8217;re lecturing, but I think
that, for me at least, it would be really distracting. Having someone
else there to monitor it was really helpful. It&amp;#8217;s also a great
resource for data mining and adjusting lessons in the future, though I
will admit that I haven&amp;#8217;t had a chance to go back to my slides and
adjust.  All in all, the room worked out fine, so if there are
reservations about this in the future, it turned out (at least for us)
to be not that big of a&amp;nbsp;deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Live&amp;nbsp;tweeting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attempted to live tweet while David was teaching as well as
encouraging others to do so, as well. However, it seemed like our
audience wasn&amp;#8217;t too into it, so I personally devoted most of my time
to the Etherpad. It didn&amp;#8217;t stop me from sending a few tweets out,
though. I think in the future, I&amp;#8217;ll make more of an effort to get
participants to do this, as it&amp;#8217;s a great motivator for instructors to
do well and is great free promotion for the&amp;nbsp;organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day two started off with David teaching Python. We agreed that he&amp;#8217;ll
likely also take some time after lunch, and took a quick poll to make
sure that everyone was cool with maybe having a little less time with
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; in the afternoon. We polled also to make sure that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; was
something that they wanted because David and I kicked around spending
the whole day on Python. We all agreed: rock through all of the Python
and then introduce as much as spastically (because I was teaching?)
possible the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; portion. Again, David did a great job explaining core
Python concepts to everyone, and I had very little to do expect to
chime in with some cool tidbits about the notebook I&amp;#8217;ve come across
since it&amp;#8217;s a hugely important part of my daily workflow. I also got to
talk with some of the participants about remote notebooks and
submitting jobs into a cluster batch system, functionality that not
only to people not realize is there, but also how harnessable it all
is once you know a little bit about the IPython ecosystem. I get way
too excited about it, too, which I&amp;#8217;m sure is annoying, but I won&amp;#8217;t
apologize. IPython changed my life. There, I said&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrapped up the day by teaching through the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; lessons, actually
using the delivered bootcamp material rather than my own slides like
I did with the git lessons.  We went fast, but I tried to be engaging
and informative. I tried to drive home some of the inherent coolness
of databases in general and how they can immediately be applied, as I
have done, in common next-generation sequencing and phylogenetics
workflows. In a room full of material scientists, I was even able to
find a fellow phylogeneticist to talk to about how I handle some of my
data in git, Python, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;
(&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food"&gt;Dogfooding&lt;/a&gt;,
at it&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;best).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final&amp;nbsp;thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed teaching this bootcamp and getting to geek out with
fellow scientists for a couple of days, especially with scientists who
work in completely different areas than my own. The attendees made
this bootcamp great, too, as would be true with anything like
this. They were excited, engaged, had great questions, and were
totally appreciative of our time. It&amp;#8217;s not usually the case that one
volunteers (at least for me) with the idea that they should be
showered with praise, but it&amp;#8217;s really rewarding when you know your
time was&amp;nbsp;well-spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet and teach with David, and I learned a lot from
watching him teach a subject in which he is an expert. I also enjoyed
our conversations walking back to the hotel from campus. It would be a
pleasure to teach with him again, and I have absolutely no reservations
in recommending him as an instructor for future&amp;nbsp;bootcamps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I&amp;#8217;ll also make sure to do a better job to express the
importance of both the pre- and post-bootcamp&amp;nbsp;surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I especially want to thank Doug J., David S., and Charlotte M. for
taking such great care of us while we were there. From getting us
going in the rooms, to arranging lodging, and providing us with
amazing students, satisfying lunches, and completely essential coffee
breaks, it was a top-notch, class-act all the way. Thank you, thank
you, thank&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though my schedule is kind of absurd these days, I&amp;#8217;ll be sure to carve
out as much time as I can in the future to be able to teach one of
these bootcamps again (and hopefully it won&amp;#8217;t be too long, hint.). It
was&amp;nbsp;privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="swcarpentry"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="sql"></category><category term="python"></category></entry><entry><title>Drying silica beads in the microwave</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Jul/28/drying-silica-beads-in-the-microwave/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-07-28T10:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-28T10:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-07-28:/posts/2014/Jul/28/drying-silica-beads-in-the-microwave/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, this is a new fun one. As I need to get my butt back out in the
field again, having used all of the silica beads in previous trips
(between Brandon and I) to keep our needles dry, we were faced with
two obvious choices: buy new or reuse …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, this is a new fun one. As I need to get my butt back out in the
field again, having used all of the silica beads in previous trips
(between Brandon and I) to keep our needles dry, we were faced with
two obvious choices: buy new or reuse. Being the thrifty scientists
that we are (hey, we are supported by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt;, after all), you can
probably guess which way we went. Plus, silica is darn expensive, and
we&amp;#8217;d much rather spend our lab money on more critical supplies&amp;nbsp;(beer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with the awesomeness of silica beads, we buy them
in bulk with an indicator: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OITND&lt;/span&gt; (Orange is the New Dry). Actually, no
one actually knows what the chemical is (lies!), but when it&amp;#8217;s wet, it
loses it&amp;#8217;s color. Good enough for&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/silica_bulk.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you put pine needles into 15 ml tubes containing about 6 ml of
gel beads, it&amp;#8217;s only a matter of time, due to continued transpiration,
that they will get fully hydrated. This is great; they&amp;#8217;ve done their
job, but using beads only once is hugely expensive
(&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/55LBS-Orange-Moisture-Indicating-Silica/dp/B00656VZO8"&gt;$350.00&lt;/a&gt;
for 55 lbs). Hence, the&amp;nbsp;re-dry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes without saying that having a great undergrad in the lab who
can take tasks and run with them, makes getting dry beads a snap for
high-end postdocs like myself (&lt;em&gt;snicker&lt;/em&gt;). Alice did a great job of
getting this working efficiently, so I wanted to share it with you,
all three of you (including my parents) who read this&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes a little something like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove the beads from current tubes and pour them into something
convenient to store them before&amp;nbsp;drying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get a 13x9x2 Pyrex baking&amp;nbsp;dish&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour (carefully, as they get bouncy) a nice single layer of&amp;nbsp;beads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set your microwave to medium (our setting is 5/10, but &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YMMV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cook the beads for 3&amp;nbsp;minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take out and give a good stir.  We
use a technical piece of equipment designed for stirring, like a
ruler. (&lt;em&gt;Note: be careful, the beads get wicked hot!&lt;/em&gt;). Some sticking
is normal, but be careful. If they get too hot and burn, they are&amp;nbsp;ruined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cook for another 3 minutes on&amp;nbsp;medium&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stir again (see&amp;nbsp;above)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go another minute if necessary (we do, but again, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YMMV&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes right, you should have a nice, orange, ready-to-go set of
beads.  All that&amp;#8217;s left to do is put them into new tubes and organize
them (into sets of 5, in my case). If your undergrad is as good as
Alice, you can get about 50 lbs of silica dried and put into 100
groups of 5 in about a&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="lab"></category></entry><entry><title>Recap of my talk on 4/25/14 at CCTL</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Apr/28/recap-of-my-talk-on-42514-at-cctl/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-28T10:21:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-28T10:21:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-04-28:/posts/2014/Apr/28/recap-of-my-talk-on-42514-at-cctl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=http://iss.schoolwires.com/Domain/3495 border=0 target=_new&gt;
&lt;img src=http://iss.schoolwires.com/cms/lib4/NC01000579/Centricity/Template/3//logos/cctl.jpg
width="500px"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, I suppose I should title this &amp;#8220;Evolution of the trees of
the cosmos.&amp;#8221; More on why in a little&amp;nbsp;bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the span of about a year, I have been thinking about
putting together a series of talks for advanced high
school students to stress the importance of having …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=http://iss.schoolwires.com/Domain/3495 border=0 target=_new&gt;
&lt;img src=http://iss.schoolwires.com/cms/lib4/NC01000579/Centricity/Template/3//logos/cctl.jpg
width="500px"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, I suppose I should title this &amp;#8220;Evolution of the trees of
the cosmos.&amp;#8221; More on why in a little&amp;nbsp;bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the span of about a year, I have been thinking about
putting together a series of talks for advanced high
school students to stress the importance of having a
working knowledge of mathematical concepts in order
to &amp;#8220;do&amp;#8221; science. More recently, it occurred to me that
this was a statement only really directed toward
students who were already interested in studying
science and not necessarily toward others, like
students interested in pursuing mathematics as a
career but who never thought of applying their
skills in the biological sciences (where, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IMO&lt;/span&gt;,
these skills are both needed and highly sought). I&amp;#8217;m
still trying to balance these priorities in my head,
getting science kids to recognize the importance of
math and getting math kids to realize that they,
too, have a place in science (biological sciences,
in particular). I say, &amp;#8220;kids&amp;#8221;, in the most
well-intentioned, non-condescending way possible, by
the way.
So, with little more than a concept in mind, I approached
two people: my wife&amp;#8217;s cousin Lauren (a math teacher in
Richmond, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt;) and my friend Brooke, (a math teacher in
Statesville, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NC&lt;/span&gt;). Brooke, incidentally, is married to
a childhood friend of both my wife and me, Matt. Matt
and Brooke are also amazing hosts, so visiting them
at their home would be yet another benefit of the&amp;nbsp;trip!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordinating with the folks at Brooke&amp;#8217;s school, the
&lt;a href="http://iss.schoolwires.com/Domain/3495"&gt;Collaborative College for Technology &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Leadership
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCTL&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;,
an Early College High School in Statesville, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NC&lt;/span&gt;, was a
wonderful experience. Within a few days of initially contacting
them, we had the principal on board, as well as Britainy the
science teacher, a room, and a good plan on how to proceed.
It was their idea to combine their respective classes for the
day, and we set up three one-hour slots for me to speak to the
groups of students. I&amp;#8217;m still waiting to hear back from the
teachers in &lt;a href="http://www.henrico.k12.va.us"&gt;Henrico&lt;/a&gt; (hint!),
but I&amp;#8217;m hopeful that we can coordinate something before the
end of the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spring, except for the fine coating of pollen on everything,
is a fantastic time of year in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NC&lt;/span&gt;, and I took full advantage
of it by riding down on my new &lt;a href="/images/triumph.png"&gt;Triumph&lt;/a&gt;
(much to my wife&amp;#8217;s dismay). The weather was in the 70&amp;#8217;s and 80&amp;#8217;s,
and it was an amazing ride on country roads and through small
towns. I really also dig &amp;#8220;The Wave,&amp;#8221; and
did my fair share of crotch-rocket snubbery. Arriving a little
late into Matt and Brooke&amp;#8217;s led to characteristic revelry, and the
6 a.m. wake-up call came very, very&amp;nbsp;quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use Prezi for my talk, a first for me, as I
normally tend to err more on the side of scientific
content than entertainment value, but it was a
good experience. I&amp;#8217;ve embedded it here, in case anyone
wants to have a&amp;nbsp;look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/-qygo8d1jasu/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;amp;
lock_to_path=0&amp;amp;autoplay=0&amp;amp;
autohide_ctrls=0&amp;amp;features=undefined&amp;amp;disabled_features=undefined"
width="550" height="400" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen
mozAllowFullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that might jump out to you immediately, is the lack
of a proper title. I did this on purpose - not simply because
I was too lazy to do this job myself, but I wanted to make
sure that my message got across. A cheap trick? Maybe. Was
it useful? Maybe - but since I forgot to circle back to it
the first two times I gave the talk, it&amp;#8217;s hard to know. The quote
at the beginning of this post (that I said I&amp;#8217;d come back to) is
one of the options the third group came up with. Not too shabby,
and it certainly proves that I&amp;#8217;m not invisible and that they were
paying&amp;nbsp;attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk was outlined as below. For the first time giving it, I think
that all of the pieces were there that I wanted to cover.  However,
there was a lot of info - perhaps too much. Anyway, here it&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My educational and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; backgrounds - I think this is useful for
students to hear for a couple of reasons. First, to emphasize
that I &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; I knew what I wanted to do (eye doctor), made a
plan, executed that plan, then drastically changed that&amp;nbsp;plan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My master&amp;#8217;s work - to show some practical application of
math and algorithms operating on biological (gene expression)&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Ph.D. work - introduction to molecular evolution, sequence
conservation, and the enormity of tree space. All of this
was meant to generate questions at the end and drive home
the need for more work in areas of algorithm, computation,
and the need to understand both math and science to do the&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Postdoc - talk about variation, a cool quantitative
character (bark thickness) in light of an interesting ecological
driver of evolutionary change (fire). Also to demonstrate some
real-world applications of mathematical concepts they were
learning now (getting tree height using a&amp;nbsp;clinometer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant topics in evolution - I chose three to illustrate
how evolutionary thinking informs modern research: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HIV&lt;/span&gt; transmission,
(Castro-Nallar, et al., 2012, The evolution of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HIV&lt;/span&gt;: inferences using
phylogenetics, Molecular phylogenetics and evolution, 62(2), pp. 777-92.)
language spread (Bouckaert, et al., 2012, Mapping the origins and
expansion of the Indo-European language family, Science, 337(6097),
pp. 957-60.), and deep-time ancestry (Williams, et. al., 2013, An archaeal
origin of eukaryotes supports only two primary domains of life,
Nature, 504(7479), pp.&amp;nbsp;231-6.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I talked about how wonderful the show
&lt;a href="http://www.cosmosontv.com"&gt;Cosmos&lt;/a&gt; is. A good many students already
watched it (which is awesome!), and I hope I turned new students on
to the&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also put some of my favorite science-y quotes in there for good&amp;nbsp;measure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Nothing makes sense in biology except in the light of evolution,
&lt;em&gt;sub specie evolutionis&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221; -Dobzhansky&amp;nbsp;(1964)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Essentially, all models are wrong, but some are useful.&amp;#8221; -Box&amp;nbsp;(1987)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;We live in a society exquisitely dependent on science and technology,
in which hardly anyone knows anything about science and technology.&amp;#8221;
-Sagan&amp;nbsp;(1990)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I was happy with how the talks went, though I did have to
adapt the content throughout the morning. Here are a few of my&amp;nbsp;observations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first talk spent too much time outlining my
previous history.  I didn&amp;#8217;t have enough time to talk about my
current work and spend much time on the current topics. I also
only had about 10 minutes for questions, which went&amp;nbsp;quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first talk contained way too many attempts
at thinly-veiled humor. It just simply was too early, and
in no way am I just &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ripped through the third iteration of the talk and left about
30 minutes for questions. The students had insightful questions and we
had a lively  discussion. It made me wish I could have talked longer,
to give them more information, but I was glad for the interaction, and
was surprised by how willing the students were to engage with me. Along
those lines, here are some of my favorite, perhaps somewhat unexpected,&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were you like when you were in 9th&amp;nbsp;grade?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you had any issues with your&amp;nbsp;appearance?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did you decide on your area of&amp;nbsp;research?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;#8217;s more important, math or&amp;nbsp;science?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you had the opportunity, would you choose to go to a school like
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCTL&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you believe we will find a cure for&amp;nbsp;cancer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you recommend going into the medical&amp;nbsp;field?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that I gave adequate answers to these questions. I was
immediately struck by how open the students were, especially the
9th graders. There is no way I would have been so forward and
fearless with a Ph.D. in front of the room when I was their age. It was
completely refreshing in a &amp;#8220;there&amp;#8217;s still hope for humanity&amp;#8221; kind of
way. The students should feel proud for both representing themselves
intelligently and as shining ambassadors for their school. If
everyone there is like these groups of students, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCTL&lt;/span&gt; is certainly doing
things&amp;nbsp;right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the student who asked me about curing cancer: my family, too, has been
greatly affected by cancer, and I&amp;#8217;ve been dealing with it on a daily
basis since 1996. My mother was diagnosed with Multiple Myeloma when I
was a freshman in college, and my father had renal cancer resulting in having
his kidney removed a couple of years ago now. I hope that my answer wasn&amp;#8217;t flip,
because I certainly didn&amp;#8217;t mean it to be. My best to you and your family.
My mother has outlived all of the current research, and my father is also
currently doing well, so there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; hope. Hang in&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To the students and teachers at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCTL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: I am in your debt. Thank you
so much for allowing me to crash your morning on an early-release day and
for the opportunity to talk about my work and my field. I hope you learned
something from me because I know that I did from you. Please also feel
free to leave comments on this post so we can continue our&amp;nbsp;dialog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="talks"></category><category term="nsf"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="math"></category><category term="evolution"></category></entry><entry><title>I am not a bioinformatician</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Jan/22/i-am-not-a-bioinformatician/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-22T14:50:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-22T14:50:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-01-22:/posts/2014/Jan/22/i-am-not-a-bioinformatician/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, so I suppose this requires some clarification. Last 
week, I attended &lt;a href="http://www.intlpag.org"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAGXXII&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in San Diego. 
Overall, it was a good experience.  Given that I have no choice 
of going for the next two years, as a condition of my 
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt; fellowship, I&amp;#8217;ll be looking forward to some sun …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, so I suppose this requires some clarification. Last 
week, I attended &lt;a href="http://www.intlpag.org"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAGXXII&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in San Diego. 
Overall, it was a good experience.  Given that I have no choice 
of going for the next two years, as a condition of my 
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt; fellowship, I&amp;#8217;ll be looking forward to some sun 
next January.  This being my first major conference as a 
postdoc, I was characteristically terrible at 
networking, probably talked too much at the bar each night, 
and spent too much time sitting in meetings rather than 
building scientific collaborations in the&amp;nbsp;sunshine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to lots of talks at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAG&lt;/span&gt; that focused on, well, what 
I would call &amp;#8220;bean-counting.&amp;#8221;  You&amp;#8217;ve been there, yearning 
for biological or evolutionary insight from the newly 
assembled or annotated genome, only to sit there 
though talk after talk of &amp;#8220;The N50 was&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;At 100X coverage 
we managed to assemble 14M contigs&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;  While these data 
are no doubt valuable to the scientific process, it does 
fall a little flat after awhile.  Give me some description 
of a novel pathway, what makes your study system special, how 
can this be applied to a more broad class of organisms, something, 
dear god something, other than N50 and contig number and length&amp;nbsp;distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that mini-rant out of the way, I had a chance encounter 
with a scientist from a well-known lab, studying some of the 
same trees as we do, who earlier in the week, saw me talking 
to another member of his lab.  I was sitting at the bar, having 
a snack before the banquet, and he said something like, &amp;#8220;I saw 
you talking to so-and-so, and you&amp;#8217;re the &amp;#8216;bioinformatician&amp;#8217; 
working with Andrew, right?&amp;#8221;  Just then, I died a little inside. 
In fact, the same thing happened at the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt; awardee meeting in the 
fall, when the program officer told a room full of other awardees
(read: professional and admirable scientists) that I was a 
bioinformatician, and that my proposal was funded partly 
because I brought a different level of experience to the 
plant genomics community (the addressing of fundamental 
evolutionary questions and specific, testable hypotheses, 
notwithstanding, of&amp;nbsp;course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s my perspective.  Yes, I used to do lots of fancy &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;. 
Yes, I know my way around several operating systems and know 
a few programming languages. Yes, I have a masters in bioinformatics 
in addition to a Ph.D. Yes, I write code every day. Yes, I write 
this code (usually) to analyze biological data.  So, why am I not a 
bioinformatician, then?  Why don&amp;#8217;t I just shut up and stop being 
such an elitist?  As it turns out, the former question is much easier 
to address than the latter (snicker).  Let me say first, before anyone 
gets their feelings hurt, that &lt;strong&gt;there is nothing wrong with being a 
bioinformatician&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The venerable Wikipedia defines 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bioinformatics"&gt;bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; as: &amp;#8220;an 
interdisciplinary scientific field that develops methods for storing, 
retrieving, organizing and analyzing biological data.&amp;#8221;  You can read 
the wiki, if you desire, but the short of it is (at least for me) is 
that I am interested in the &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; of the system, not simply the 
techniques (developed either by me or someone else) used in the analysis 
process.  I want to understand the &lt;strong&gt;biology&lt;/strong&gt;, and that happens to come 
along, these days, with the (un)fortunate burden of huge data&amp;nbsp;sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, a bioinformatician is someone who works in conjunction with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PI&lt;/span&gt; 
(I do include myself in this category) and provides a service (sometimes 
even a valuable one), where that service is needed.  Bioinformaticians 
tend to prioritize data generation and methodology execution higher than 
biological insight. They are the &amp;#8220;Methods&amp;#8221; section rather than the 
&amp;#8220;Discussion&amp;#8221; section.  It&amp;#8217;s also been my (probably extremely 
rare and biased) experience here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCU&lt;/span&gt; that 
the &lt;em&gt;bioinformaticians&lt;/em&gt; with whom I have had the pleasure to 
interact, either (or in some&amp;nbsp;combination):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t know what they&amp;#8217;re doing (which is&amp;nbsp;bad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think they know what they&amp;#8217;re doing (which is&amp;nbsp;worse)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide inadequate customer service (in a service-oriented&amp;nbsp;role)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t play well with others (read: huge&amp;nbsp;ego)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overstay their welcome and/or overestimate their&amp;nbsp;contributions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if I&amp;#8217;m not a bioinformatician, then what (other than elitist, jerk, etc.)? 
What do I tell my in-laws, friends, relatives, or the occasional stranger at a bar? 
Usually, I say that &lt;strong&gt;I am a scientist&lt;/strong&gt;, further probing leads me into &lt;strong&gt;evolutionary 
biologist&lt;/strong&gt; (where my main passions lie) or &lt;strong&gt;computational biologist&lt;/strong&gt; (for 
practicality).  If I really don&amp;#8217;t care to talk at that moment, I&amp;#8217;ll even fall back 
on &lt;strong&gt;postdoc&lt;/strong&gt;, but people either don&amp;#8217;t know what that is, or think it has 
something to do with a Ph.D., but upon further inspection of my person, let&amp;#8217;s face it, 
doesn&amp;#8217;t often jive with stretched ears and ample&amp;nbsp;tattoos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yeah, to sum it up: I neither have said nor ever will say that I am 
&lt;em&gt;bioinformatician&lt;/em&gt; (and you shouldn&amp;#8217;t,&amp;nbsp;either).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="bnfo"></category><category term="facepalm"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry><entry><title>2013 in review</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2014/Jan/07/2013-in-review/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-07T15:19:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-07T15:19:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2014-01-07:/posts/2014/Jan/07/2013-in-review/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that the chaos of the end of the year is behind me, I thought I&amp;#8217;d 
take a step back and look at my progress (such as it was). Lots of lessons 
were learned this year, and not just scientifically. Navigating the 
inter-state bureaucracy when it comes to collecting …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that the chaos of the end of the year is behind me, I thought I&amp;#8217;d 
take a step back and look at my progress (such as it was). Lots of lessons 
were learned this year, and not just scientifically. Navigating the 
inter-state bureaucracy when it comes to collecting samples is, to put it 
nicely, slow and inconsistent. More on that&amp;nbsp;later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sampling trip #1 (a.k.a., the trip that never should have&amp;nbsp;been)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving my wife at home with our daughter while I was out in the field 
was a situation that I really wanted to avoid. So, when the opportunity 
came up for Kristin to have time off at a time when I could get into the field, 
we both jumped at it. As husbands sometimes do, I made all of the camping 
reservations for our trip without consulting anyone. The trip was to span 
a nice swathe of land across the southeast, taking us from Richmond, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt;
to South Carolina, Florida, Alabama, and Georgia. In my mind, this 
was reasonable. Hell, I was even building just travel days so our 
baby daughter didn&amp;#8217;t have to spend 12+ hours in the car. I care. I 
really do. Most of our camping was going to be done in our pop-up, 
towed lovingly by our trusty &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAAB&lt;/span&gt;. We had heat, water, power, and shelter - 
we were golden. The trip started off innocently enough, and we made it our first night stay 
without issue, if not somewhat late at night, at 
&lt;a href="http://www.reserveamerica.com/camping/The_Oaks/r/campgroundDetails.do?parkId=261505&amp;amp;contractCode=ELS2&amp;amp;chkAg=y&amp;amp;clCr=y"&gt;The Oaks&lt;/a&gt; 
in South Carolina. The next day was a drive to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FL&lt;/span&gt; to stay over at 
&lt;a href="http://www.floridastateparks.org/rainbowsprings/"&gt;Rainbow Springs&lt;/a&gt;
State Park. Again - no issues. Got in, set up camp, dinner, some wine. You know, 
roughing it. The following day was to be the first day of sampling. I was ready. 
Unfortunately, the system (read: the man) wasn&amp;#8217;t. Armed with not a single 
scientific permit (because for sure we didn&amp;#8217;t need one and for sure a hard copy 
of my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSF&lt;/span&gt; grant would suffice), I was either denied access to any state park I 
tried as well as chased from two National Forest sites. Did I mention that 
this day was also the first day of the government shutdown?  With my head 
hung low, back to the campsite I headed. Because we are both of solid German stock, 
we kept what was to be the daily itinerary of waking, sampling, packing, and driving 
(minus, of course, the sampling). Our next stop in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FL&lt;/span&gt; was a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KOA&lt;/span&gt; in Perry, but I had a 
couple of hours worth of driving from Rainbow Springs, so I did what all good Americans 
do while driving: make lots of frantic phone calls. I called the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FL&lt;/span&gt; state park offices in 
Tallahassee, The Alabama Department of Conservation of Natural Resources, and the Georgia 
Department of Natural Resources. Telling my story to endless chains of assistants was 
trying, but I eventually was able to get my hands on a last minute permit (by email) t
sample in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AL&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GA&lt;/span&gt; would have to wait, though the extremely helpful staff there (literally, 
not sarcastically) did manage to get me a rushed permit, but it ended up being too&amp;nbsp;late. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=/images/fam.jpg width="25%" style="float: right; padding: 10px;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sampling in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AL&lt;/span&gt; was great - we had beautiful weather, the 
&lt;a href="http://www.alapark.com/FrankJackson/"&gt;Frank Jackson&lt;/a&gt; State Park was completely accommodating, 
and (as I said earlier), I was ready. However, I grossly underestimated the amount of 
time sampling would take me, especially in dense forest. The goal was to sample needles and 
make other measurements (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DBH&lt;/span&gt;, height, and bark thickness) for 25 trees. Finding the trees was 
the easy part. I could do the measurements in about 2.5 minutes. Getting the needles 
with a &lt;a href="http://www.sherrilltree.com/Professional-Gear/BIGshot"&gt;Big Shot&lt;/a&gt;, however, 
was the most challenging part, taking my 2.5 minutes/tree up to sometimes 20 before 
I could move on. Given that math, I realized I would going to be at this for a long 
time (and not just that day, but more like on the scale of years) before it was all 
said and done. Starting late that first day, I worked until dark, and nearly finished. 
Nearly, because, well, this&amp;nbsp;happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristin was cleaning a wine glass, the baby was having some lunch, and bang!  Wine glass shatters 
off the faucet of the camper, Kristin&amp;#8217;s thumb goes right into it, completely severs a nerve, and 
bleeds like a M-F&amp;#8217;er. A frantic phone call and a trip to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ER&lt;/span&gt; (in Opp, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AL&lt;/span&gt;!) to follow. Thankfully, 
Kristin, a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CNRA&lt;/span&gt;, is well-connected. The next day, I finished sampling, and we drove 16 hours from Florala to 
Richmond so she could be seen by an expert and schedule up some&amp;nbsp;surgery. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=/images/blood.jpg width="25%", style="float: right; padding: 10px; "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all - the trip was, well, basically, a fail. I was able to get only 25 trees sampled (I anticipated 250). I did, 
however, learn some valuable&amp;nbsp;lessons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure to allow enough time for sampling and&amp;nbsp;travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure to obtain any and all permits, even if you might not need&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carry plastic wine glasses in the&amp;nbsp;camper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t bring your wife and baby on a 10-day camping/field&amp;nbsp;expedition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you do bring wife and/or baby, make sure to consult wife ahead of&amp;nbsp;time. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Collecting permits for&amp;nbsp;collection&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting permits for sampling turned out to be more of a chore than I imagined. Seems like so much 
of science, really, and at some point I suppose I&amp;#8217;ll stop getting surprised by it. For those of you 
who are reading and planning on embarking on a scientific sampling endeavor (outside of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, where, according 
to &lt;a href="http://ajeckert.blogspot.com"&gt;Andrew&lt;/a&gt;, you can pretty much sample anything as long as you&amp;#8217;re not taking seeds), 
save yourself a lot of heartache and contact the states/national offices before you go. This will save time, hassle, 
and jail time - trust me. The process is as follows&amp;nbsp;(roughly):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for the state parks you want to visit&amp;nbsp;on-line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate an unpublished and inexplicably long phone&amp;nbsp;tree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can&amp;#8217;t find a phone number, find an&amp;nbsp;email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can&amp;#8217;t find an email, call the park reservation&amp;nbsp;line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you find the right person, find out what they need from you. In my case, my grant application, approval letter, 
and a page or two of description did the&amp;nbsp;trick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submit applications, pay (if required), and wait (up to a month or&amp;nbsp;more). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the approved permits also come with some strings attached. For some states, I&amp;#8217;m required to renew early/often, 
provide detailed reports, and/or speak at their meetings about my project. Most places require that I give 
them advanced notice of when I&amp;#8217;m going to be at their location. Luckily, it seems like they&amp;#8217;re cool with approximations and 
it really does come in handy when the park is expecting your visit. Usually, they also want to know what sites you plan 
on visiting rather than, say, &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;d really like a permit to visit any state park in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FL&lt;/span&gt; for the next year.&amp;#8221;  For national parks, 
it&amp;#8217;s a little more complicated. In my case, I submitted an application for the entire region 8 which covers any site I might 
want to visit in the southeast. As of today, I have permits to sample (at some point this year) at select state parks&amp;nbsp;in: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alabama&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arkansas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Florida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Louisiana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tennessee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Texas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The permit for the National Forest Service, Mississippi, North Carolina, and Virginia are still pending. 
Applications to Delaware, South Carolina, and Maryland will be submitted by the end of this&amp;nbsp;month. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sampling trip #2 (a.k.a., two pining&amp;nbsp;boys)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With sampling permits in hand for Arkanasa, Texas, and Louisiana, &lt;a href="http://bmlind.blogspot.com"&gt;Brandon&lt;/a&gt; and I set 
out after his last final was done. An epic drive later, through torrential rain in Tennessee, had us 
sleeping on the ground in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt;, on ice, in tents. See, it was my original plan to sample further south in 
the winter, foolishly thinking that it might just be a little warmer. So, so wrong. We woke up to this 
&lt;a href="/images/son.jpg"&gt;nice young man and his dog&lt;/a&gt; (who can play dead better than a possum) and set off 
to get some sampling done after downing a few pots of french press, locally-roasted Richmond coffee, 
and frosted Pop-Tarts. Remember how much I rough it?  We were in loblolly country, and got our first 
population of the trip done in relatively short order (about 5 hours) at 
&lt;a href="http://www.arkansasstateparks.com/pinnaclemountain/"&gt;Pinnacle Mountain State Park&lt;/a&gt;. The staff there 
was super friendly, and very interested in what I was out there doing. It was great to talk about 
the project to some enthusiastic young people!   The plan for this trip was basically the same as 
the trip which shall not be named - drive, sample, drive. The next stop was &lt;a href="http://www.arkansasstateparks.com/lakeouachita/"&gt;Lake Ouachita 
State Park&lt;/a&gt;, and boy was it cold (like single digits, cold!). 
A good campfire, some dinner, a little Woodford, and day two was done. Sampling at the state park was a bust, 
but an employee pointed us to the Ouachita National Forest, which was just overflowing with nice stands of loblolly. 
With sampling done there, and a quick afternoon coffee break out of the back of the car (French press + Camelback water + 
coffee + propane stove), we were on our way into&amp;nbsp;Texas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got into &lt;a href="http://www.tpwd.state.tx.us/state-parks/atlanta"&gt;Atlanta State Park&lt;/a&gt;, or as it shall now be known, 
the &amp;#8220;Park of the 1000 Howling Coyotes.&amp;#8221;  We rocked a huge &lt;a href="/images/atlanta_fire.jpg"&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt; that night, some burgers, 
I attempted in vain to order Christmas presents from my tent on a single bar of Edge over &lt;a href="http://www.tether.com"&gt;Tether&lt;/a&gt;. 
No longer in the throngs of Arkansas winter, Texas was shaping up to be not too shabby, despite the 
inability to buy beer, after 6:00pm, on a Sunday. Sampling here was a non-issue, and we were soon headed 
south about 240 miles to &lt;a href="http://www.tpwd.state.tx.us/state-parks/village-creek"&gt;Village Creek State Park&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due in part to a late start, we decided late in the day to stay another night and get the first longleaf 
population in addition to the loblolly we sampled the first day. 
&lt;img src=/images/brandon.jpg width="25%" style="float: right; padding: 10px;"&gt; 
The trail system at the park was really nice, 
and we only got off trail once on the second day, and we had a good laugh about two PhDs being found 
dead in the woods with fully charged iPhones and 4 bars of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTE&lt;/span&gt;. Down a trail about 2 miles, we found an 
&lt;a href="/images/longleaf_savannah.jpg"&gt;area that was being reforested&lt;/a&gt;, with natural stands of longleaf. Thinking we were golden, 
we sampled 12 in addition to the 25 loblollys on the first day, planned to get the second half the next day before 
heading into Louisiana. Well, you know the saying about paving and best intentions? Because I&amp;#8217;m being careful 
to control for kinship, I&amp;#8217;m sampling only from trees more than 50m apart, and when you consider 25 trees in a 
population, that gets to be a pretty big area (there&amp;#8217;s a good math problem there, methinks). So, on day two, 
we only ended up with a total of 17 longleafs. Not a huge deal, but boo&amp;nbsp;anyway. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With many beers in tow after the worlds longest fill-up before leaving &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TX&lt;/span&gt;, we got to 
&lt;a href="http://www.crt.state.la.us/parks/ishjones.aspx"&gt;Sam Houston Jones State Park&lt;/a&gt;. As with the other places, 
they were expecting me, and could not have been nicer. The park sits right on top of an old longleaf 
savannah, and sampling here was a great way to end our trip. We had lunch at 
&lt;a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/botskys-lake-charles?nb=1"&gt;Botsky&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; and dinner the first night at 
the &lt;a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/seafood-palace-lake-charles?nb=1"&gt;Seafood Palace&lt;/a&gt;, both of which were awesome.
The weather for sampling the next day could not have been better - sunny and warm! Finally, we had the weather 
I thought we&amp;#8217;d have for the entire trip. Out of time, we needed to get back to Richmond by Friday evening. We 
left Sam Houston Jones, had boudin/cracklin&amp;#8217; dinner at &lt;a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/best-stop-supermarket-the-scott?nb=1"&gt;Best Stop&lt;/a&gt; 
in Scott, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LA&lt;/span&gt; (thanks to the guy at Botsky&amp;#8217;s for the tip!), set up camp at some place in Mississippi about 1/3 of the way home, 
and drove the remainder on Friday. This trip yielded some new insights as&amp;nbsp;well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going into the field with someone else is much more fun and enjoyable than going&amp;nbsp;alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brandon is a pro with the Big&amp;nbsp;Shot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will never be as good as Brandon with the Big&amp;nbsp;Shot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold Bourbon is just not all that&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We could really only get down to 10 min/tree. Meaning 2 populations/day is damn near 
impossible with the winter&amp;nbsp;daylight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a team of&amp;nbsp;people. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we were able to sample six populations in six days for a total of 142 trees.  Add that to my previous from 
the trip that shall not be named, and that brings the total to &lt;strong&gt;167&lt;/strong&gt; (out of&amp;nbsp;2000&amp;#8230;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow - longness. If you made it this far, you deserve a &amp;#8220;Happy New Year!&amp;#8221; Here&amp;#8217;s to a much more productive&amp;nbsp;2014!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This is not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; that we did in 2013, but look for those papers soon to be out in journals near you, this&amp;nbsp;spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and thanks to everyone at the state parks and departments who were so&amp;nbsp;helpful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;Chris&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="field"></category><category term="permits"></category><category term="gore"></category><category term="loblolly"></category><category term="longleaf"></category></entry><entry><title>Managing IPython notebooks with GitHub</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2013/Jul/10/managing-ipython-notebooks-with-github/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-10T10:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-07-10T10:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2013-07-10:/posts/2013/Jul/10/managing-ipython-notebooks-with-github/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the process of moving all of my new code to GitHub, I started thinking about how I 
wanted to manage things like my IPython notebooks. Previoulsy, with my code 
on &lt;a href="http://bitbucket.org/cfriedline"&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;, I created a single hg &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/cfriedline/cluster_ipynb"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt; 
for all of my notebooks on our cluster. Given that the notebooks …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the process of moving all of my new code to GitHub, I started thinking about how I 
wanted to manage things like my IPython notebooks. Previoulsy, with my code 
on &lt;a href="http://bitbucket.org/cfriedline"&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;, I created a single hg &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/cfriedline/cluster_ipynb"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt; 
for all of my notebooks on our cluster. Given that the notebooks have to live in a single 
directory for every instance of the notebook, I did that to avoid having to run multiple notebook 
processes for each of the notebooks I was working&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It occured to me today that there is another possible solution to this, and one I&amp;#8217;ll be using 
for all of my new code (which will be on &lt;a href="http://github.com/cfriedline"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;). The process looks 
like this, and seems much less messy from a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch a notebook process on the cluster (or use an existing&amp;nbsp;one)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new notebook&amp;nbsp;file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new directory on the cluster to house the 
notebook file (with &lt;code&gt;touch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;#8216;&lt;/span&gt;ed &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; files)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move the notebook to this&amp;nbsp;directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new repo on&amp;nbsp;GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;git add .&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git remote add origin&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Symlink the &lt;code&gt;.ipynb&lt;/code&gt; file back into the directory from where the notebook is&amp;nbsp;running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems to work great. Note that deleting the notebook from the Dashboard will only 
delete the symlink, not the notebook itself. Maybe a safety feature, maybe an annoyance, but 
only time will tell. Simple&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ipython"></category><category term="git"></category></entry><entry><title>IPython notebook with Sun Grid Engine</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2013/Jul/09/ipython-notebook-with-sun-grid-engine/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-09T15:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-07-09T15:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2013-07-09:/posts/2013/Jul/09/ipython-notebook-with-sun-grid-engine/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCU&lt;/span&gt;, we have what some might call a high performance computing center. While 
this is largely true, there are many limitations to how the current system is 
deployed and managed.  My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; background has made working 
around these limitations somewhat easier, though no less of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PITA&lt;/span&gt;.  Hopefully …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCU&lt;/span&gt;, we have what some might call a high performance computing center. While 
this is largely true, there are many limitations to how the current system is 
deployed and managed.  My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; background has made working 
around these limitations somewhat easier, though no less of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PITA&lt;/span&gt;.  Hopefully, 
some of these tips can help others, as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this tutorial, I will assume that you have Python 2.7.x 
installed with IPython.  I&amp;#8217;ve been using the fabulous Enthought Python 
Distribution (a.k.a. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPD&lt;/span&gt;) for quite some time, which gets me most of the 
way there.  As I like living on the edge, I run IPython from the git repo. However, 
the setup described here should largely be the same regardless of the version 
of IPython you choose to&amp;nbsp;run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A current limitation of IPython notebooks is that they must be served 
from a single directory, which presents an interesting paradigm with 
respect to version control.  This can be managed in multiple&amp;nbsp;ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have all notebooks installed in a single folder and version 
control at the top level of the folder, including all *.ipynb&amp;nbsp;files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a folder for each notebook and tie it to an individual running 
notebook&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these are possible, and working with either scenario should hopefully 
be clear by the end of this document.  If not, definitely check out the 
&lt;a href="http://ipython.org/ipython-doc/dev/config/index.html"&gt;IPython documentation&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Create an IPython&amp;nbsp;profile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ipython profile create --parallel --profile=sge
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will create a profile as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPYTHONDIR&lt;/span&gt;/profile_sge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Edit the cluster profile&amp;nbsp;file&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open &lt;code&gt;ipcluster_config.py&lt;/code&gt; and make the following&amp;nbsp;edits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;c.IPClusterEngines.engine_launcher_class = &amp;quot;SGEEngineSetLauncher&amp;quot;
c.IPClusterStart.controller_launcher_class = &amp;quot;SGEControllerLauncher&amp;quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This setting enables submitting the controller and engines as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SGE&lt;/span&gt; qsub&amp;nbsp;jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Edit the notebook profile&amp;nbsp;file&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open &lt;code&gt;ipython_notebook_config.py&lt;/code&gt; and make the following&amp;nbsp;edits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;c.NotebookApp.password = ...
c.NotebookManager.save_script=True
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first line sets a password to use for the notebook.  How to do this is 
in the &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/ipython-doc/dev/interactive/htmlnotebook.html#security"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
The second line saves the notebook out as a Python file for use later.  None of these are 
necessarily important for running with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SGE&lt;/span&gt;, but I&amp;#8217;m noting them here&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Hack the IPython&amp;nbsp;frontend&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our cluster setup has compute nodes which all have access to any one of several 
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NFS&lt;/span&gt; mounts.  While this is somewhat of a generic setup, a &lt;em&gt;feature&lt;/em&gt; which can 
result is a write delay of the controller and engine scripts that get dropped 
when starting a cluster from the notebook. To get around this, I made an edit to 
&lt;code&gt;lib/python2.7/site-packages/IPython/html/services/clusters/clustermanager.py&lt;/code&gt; which 
changes &lt;code&gt;delay = CFloat(1., config=True,...)&lt;/code&gt; to delay = CFloat(30., config=True,&amp;#8230;).
This effectively will, when a cluster is initiated from the notebook, start a controller 
process via qsub, wait 30 seconds, then start the array job for the engines. This is a 
definite hack, and I&amp;#8217;d like to see it implemented as a feature sometime in the future. I 
should probably file a&amp;nbsp;bug&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The previous location for this setting (0.13.x - ?) was here:
&lt;code&gt;lib/python2.7/site-packages/IPython/frontend/html/notebook/clustermanager.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Create scripts to start the&amp;nbsp;job&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created two scripts to start the notebook process on the&amp;nbsp;cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;notebook_qsub.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
qsub -cwd -V -N inotebook start_notebook.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;start_notebook.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
ipython notebook --pylab inline --no-browser --profile&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;sge
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put both of these scripts in the folder which will house my notebooks (see options 
above), make them both executable (&lt;code&gt;chmod +x&lt;/code&gt;).  Because I&amp;#8217;m passing &lt;code&gt;-cwd&lt;/code&gt;, these scripts 
will operate from the current working directory (i.e., where the ipynb files&amp;nbsp;are).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Start the&amp;nbsp;notebook&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting the notebook is simple now.  I just cd to the directory where the notebooks are 
and run &lt;code&gt;./notebook_qub.sh&lt;/code&gt;.  Assuming all goes well, I should now have my notebook process, 
named &amp;#8220;inotebook&amp;#8221;, showing up when running &lt;code&gt;qstat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Connect to the&amp;nbsp;notebook&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the notebook process will now be running on a compute node, which is not accessible 
from the outside network.  To enable access from my machine, I do a little &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSH&lt;/span&gt; tunneling magic.  It 
goes like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open up your .ssh/config and make the following&amp;nbsp;edits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Host &amp;lt;submitnode&amp;gt;
User &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;
HostName &amp;lt;fully.qualified.domain.name.of.submitnode&amp;gt;

Host &amp;lt;computenode&amp;gt;
User &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;
ProxyCommand ssh &amp;lt;submitnode&amp;gt; -W %h:22
LocalForward localhost:8888 localhost:8888
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will enable you to &lt;code&gt;ssh &amp;lt;computenode&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and tunnel the connection through the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;submitnode&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to which 
you already have access.  The port will be forwarded, through, as well, so all you need to do is now is fire-up 
your favorite, websocket-enabled browser, and hit &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8888&lt;/code&gt;. You should now also be able to go the Clusters tab and fire up a cluster.  If you &lt;code&gt;watch qstat&lt;/code&gt;, you should see 
the controller job start, wait, and then the engines will&amp;nbsp;start.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m definitely making some assumptions here about architecture and that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSH&lt;/span&gt; forwarding is enabled in your 
environment. Your mileage may vary, but I hope this gives a good overview of what my process looks like. 
More about this problem can be found on my 
&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/15376992/starting-an-ipython-cluster-from-the-notebook-with-a-delay"&gt;StackExchange post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ipython"></category><category term="sge"></category></entry><entry><title>New paper accepted to Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2013/Jul/03/new-paper-accepted-to-orphanet-journal-of-rare-diseases/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-03T12:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-07-03T12:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2013-07-03:/posts/2013/Jul/03/new-paper-accepted-to-orphanet-journal-of-rare-diseases/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Gilbreath&amp;#8217;s paper, &lt;em&gt;A Core Microbiome Associated with the Peritoneal Tumors of 
Pseudomyxoma Peritonei&lt;/em&gt;, on which I am an author, has been accepted to &lt;a href="http://www.ojrd.com"&gt;Orphanet Journal of 
Rare Diseases&lt;/a&gt;.  Jeremy was my roommate at &lt;a href="http://molevol.mbl.edu"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOLE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href="http://stamps.mbl.edu"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;STAMPS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2011, and I&amp;#8217;m proud to collaborate with him and the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Gilbreath&amp;#8217;s paper, &lt;em&gt;A Core Microbiome Associated with the Peritoneal Tumors of 
Pseudomyxoma Peritonei&lt;/em&gt;, on which I am an author, has been accepted to &lt;a href="http://www.ojrd.com"&gt;Orphanet Journal of 
Rare Diseases&lt;/a&gt;.  Jeremy was my roommate at &lt;a href="http://molevol.mbl.edu"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOLE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href="http://stamps.mbl.edu"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;STAMPS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2011, and I&amp;#8217;m proud to collaborate with him and the others.&lt;br&gt;
Congrats,&amp;nbsp;Jeremy!  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="microbiome"></category></entry><entry><title>First post</title><link href="http://chris.friedline.net/posts/2013/Jul/03/first-post/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-03T10:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-07-03T10:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Friedline</name></author><id>tag:chris.friedline.net,2013-07-03:/posts/2013/Jul/03/first-post/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After much research, toil, and soul-searching, I&amp;#8217;ve decided to start
this blog as a way to both chronicle my postdoctoral endeavors and
introduce myself (in a way) to the larger scientific community.  I
hope that people will find my writings useful, informative, and
entertaining.  Hopefully, sometimes things will get …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After much research, toil, and soul-searching, I&amp;#8217;ve decided to start
this blog as a way to both chronicle my postdoctoral endeavors and
introduce myself (in a way) to the larger scientific community.  I
hope that people will find my writings useful, informative, and
entertaining.  Hopefully, sometimes things will get controversial and
we can have meaningful dialogs.  Or, maybe you can just call me&amp;nbsp;names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about doing this for a while now, but it just
seemed a little self-aggrandizing to do so when I was still a student.
Now that I&amp;#8217;m a fully-minted, Ph.D., however, everyone &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; care
about everything I have to say, right?  &lt;em&gt;Hardly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve chosen to blog on the &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; platform.
I looked around at the alternatives (Wordpress, Blogger, Jekyll,
Octopress, Hyde), and this seemed like the best fit.  Everything seems
to play nicely together, even with
&lt;a href="https://www.enthought.com/products/canopy/"&gt;Canopy&lt;/a&gt;, which hasn&amp;#8217;t
always the case for me.  Running right in my &lt;em&gt;User&lt;/em&gt; venv, some
installs via pip and enpkg, and I was off and running.  Even my
general distaste for all things web-development didn&amp;#8217;t stop me, and I
managed to create something that, while mostly default, at least
reflects my aesthetic.  The pages and source are hosted at
&lt;a href="http://www.github.com/cfriedline/cfriedline.github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, too,
so feel free to fork&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to hearing from people, so please get in contact
with me.  I&amp;#8217;m always open for collaboration and discussing interesting&amp;nbsp;ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>